Finding Aid for National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch Records. 1918 and 1977-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch Records 1918, 1977-1998, 1989-1998
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch.
1 items
3.75 linear feet
Volunteer and membership organization geared toward improving the educational, economic, social and political status of minorities. The records are comprised of administrative material, photographs, and files related to activities and issues.
8953 Bd 2 Bd Outsized
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were donated by the chapter in several accessions during 1998. Donor no. 8744
The collection is open for research.
In 1909, sixty prominent black and white citizens, including Ida Wells-Barnett and W.E.B. DuBois, conferred on the 100th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln's birthday and agreed to work toward the abolition of forced segregation, promotion of equal education and civil rights under the protection of law, and an end to racial violence. In 1911, the organization was incorporated as the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). In 1998, Ypsilanti-Willow Run was the fifth largest branch in Michigan and one of more than 2,200 branches governed by a national board of directors throughout the United States, the District of Columbia, Japan and Germany.
Just nine years after the national organization was launched, an Ypsilanti activist group applied for and received a chapter charter. Charles H. Mahoney, a Detroit attorney, and R.W. Bagnall, a writer, proposed the notion at a 1918 meeting organized to gather opposition to a proposed local bond issue. For forty years, black Ypsilanti children had attended an all black school until finishing the third grade. A proposed bond would raise $40,000 to include attendance at the school (which many considered severely inferior) for all the years of grammar school as well as ultimately those of high school, thereby solidifying segregated education in the community throughout the grades. Mahoney and Bagnall urged the group to organize a branch of the NAACP, fight the bond issue, and take the case of separate schools to court. Mahoney offered free legal services to the association and in time, successfully argued against the expansion of the building. Adams Street School was called both unsanitary and illegal by the court and ordered closed.
In the opinion of A. P. Marshall, a local historian, the Ypsilanti branch was only sporadically active over the next thirty years, although verification is difficult because records documenting the organization are "hard to come by." The branch was revived, however, in the late 1940s and early 1950s around racial problems in both local housing and employment. Herbert Francois started collecting dues for renewal, eventually turning over the memberships he collected to Marguerite Eaglin. Under her leadership a new charter was issued, and the organization thrived. Others active during this period included Philip Wells and Bernie Smigh.
It was also in the late forties that an NAACP branch was organized in the neighboring community of Willow Run. Discrimination in housing was the impetus that prompted leaders to purposefully gather together in the community center. Houses were being built in a region known as Washington Square, but blacks were experiencing overt bias - prospective buyers told that there were no such homes for sale or told that advertised properties had already sold. Clement Arnold and Jesse Rutherford, along with Vanzetti and Theophilus Hamilton were active in the Willow Run branch from the start, orchestrating grassroots protests and developing programs.
The NAACP in both Ypsilanti and Willow Run remained viable into the sixties, affecting change in the region into the seventies. Organizational strength was heightened however, when the two branches merged in 1982, a long-standing goal presided over by Raymond Mullins, a local attorney and chapter president, 1981 to 1982 and 1989 to 1998. Mullins, long active at the state level and on various committees (education, public relations, membership) before assuming the presidential post, was determined to expand membership and services. He focused on bringing a cross-section of the community into the organization -- bankers, chamber of commerce members, entrepreneurs, business leaders, politicians. It was Mullins' belief that the branch needed biracial support and workable coalitions, and he looked for community wide response. Membership more than doubled within a decade.
Mullin's energy and leadership molded a branch that became one of the most active in the association, winning highest honors in both 1989 and 1993 at the national level (the Thalheimer Award) for outstanding service in programmatic activities. In 1995, a year in which political action was a focal activity, the branch won the Washtenaw County Bar Association's Martin Luther King, Jr. "I Have a Dream" Award. "They have been at the very forefront of setting an example of awareness of all race, ethnic and gender bias in our community," said public defender Lloyd Powell. A key activity that year was a lobbying effort to seat black judges for the first time on the bench in Washtenaw County. Three were appointed and all successfully sought reelection.
In the eighties and nineties, the organization also concentrated on economic development (including employment outreach for young people and support for small businesses); maintained a review and referral service for civil rights complaints; assisted in referrals to community service agencies such as housing, programs for senior citizens, rehabilitation programs, legal aid, child care, job retraining, etc.; and investigated environmental issues. The later was undertaken with a grant from the Kellogg Foundation to educate the community on environmental racism and to look at issues of pollution in areas highly populated by blacks.
Youth work was also high on the agenda. In 1990, the first year of participation in ACT-SO (Afro-American, Cultural, Technological and Scientific Olympics), a national program that encourages excellence in academic and cultural pursuits, four local winners went on to compete at the annual convention. Participants sponsored by the branch won gold medals three years in a row. ACT-SO, which provides rich opportunities for students in grades nine through twelve to compete in the sciences, humanities, performing and visual arts, garnered vigorous and steadfast support from volunteers, initiated a distinctive mentoring program, and was funded by donors including General Motors, the Ford Motor Company, local financial institutions, and individuals.
During Mullins' tenure, the Ypsilanti-Willow Run NAACP participated enthusiastically and with equal success in numbers of annual programs celebrated across the nation under the national umbrella, including Jubilee Day, a commemoration of the Emancipation Proclamation on the first day of January; Black Dollar Week, a demonstration of black economic buying power; Radiothon, a fundraising and membership drive; and the Freedom Fund Dinner, which honors the anniversary of the NAACP with an added goal of raising community consciousness through sponsorships from corporations and businesses. Yet, even with all this activity requiring significant volunteer support and complex coordination, immediate local issues weren't overshadowed. In 1994, the branch facilitated the attendance of more than four hundred in the Million Man March on Washington. In 1995, it questioned the conduct of the Ann Arbor police during the investigation of a serial rapist. In 1998, it played a major role in sustaining an Ypsilanti non-discrimination ordinance protecting civil rights, including a ban on sexual orientation discrimination.
A highlight of Mullins' presidency occurred in 1994 when the branch opened its first office since establishment in 1918, thereby creating a distinct identity for the organization in the community. It housed meetings for NAACP and other community groups, provided a location for press conferences, and became a magnet for community information gathering. In its first year, it was the location for a range of exchanges on education issues, political matters, the media, women's issues, and financial planning.
The Ypsilanti-Willow Run NAACP entered a new era when Raymond Mullins, after twelve years of service, decided in 1998 to devote more time and energy to his law practice. He was succeeded by Sharon Newton Glenn, a retired Juvenile Court caseworker as president of the branch.
The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch records span the years 1918 to 1998; however there is only one item dated before 1977, the chapter charter, November 1918. The bulk of the collection documents the years 1989 to 1998.
Each aspect of the organization's mission - to work to eliminate racial prejudice; to improve the educational, economic, social and political status of minorities, to keep the public aware of the adverse effects of racial discrimination, and to take lawful action to secure the elimination of racial prejudice in a manner consistent with the national office - is well-reflected in the records, which are mainly comprised of files documenting activities and functions related to management and programming. The material arrived at the library in several accessions, and each portion contributed to an arrangement largely alphabetical. Except for files representing activities and issues, each of which are now series, the original order was maintained. There are four series in the collection: Administrative, Activities, Issues, and Photographs.
The records offer little to no documentation of the early years of the organization. (There is, however, a very brief history and an organizational resume in the administrative series.) Most of the material was produced in the 1980s and the 1990s during the twelve year leadership of Raymond Mullins. Researchers should note that the Raymond G. Mullins papers at the Bentley Historical Library include papers and clippings related to the NAACP Ypsilanti-Willow Run Branch. Researchers are also advised to consult the archivist at the Ypsilanti Historical Society for relevant material.
Subjects:
Mullins, Raymond G., 1943-; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Race relations.; Willow Run (Mich.)--Race relations.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Willow Run.; Civil rights--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Afro-Americans--Civil rights.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Ypsilanti.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-Americans--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Civil rights--Michigan--Ypsilanti.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administrative
  The Administrative series best illustrates the internal structure and workings of the organization, particularly in its constitution and bylaws, reports to the national organization (scattered), minutes of executive and general meetings, and incoming and outgoing correspondence. Correspondence files, for example, effectively illuminate the organization's concentrated effort to broaden community support for the organization. Numbers of these documents are marked as "agenda items" and similar items appear also in files containing minutes for executive and general meetings. Newsletters, initiated in 1987, are an effective vehicle for ascertaining how the branch projected itself to its membership, and press releases are a useful source for looking at the range of issues and activities it relied on the media, in a large part, to write about and help promote. Thirteen folders of newspaper clippings attest to the success of the branch in utilizing and responding to media attention. (The collection of clippings were copied onto acid-free paper and are arranged chronologically.)
  Administrative material also holds applications prepared for the prestigious Thalheimer Award, recognition bestowed annually on chapters at each national NAACP convention for outstanding programmatic activity. This is a particularly rich source. Each application includes summaries of the year's activities, offers supporting evidence, illustrates local support, and in most cases, includes photographs (photocopied onto acid-free paper) of major events. Researchers should note that a file of financial material in this series is closed until the year 2006.
  - Black Greeks 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Branches, Michigan
    - Ann Arbor 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - Detroit 1993-1996 (Box 1)
    - Establishment (Box 1)
    - Grand Rapids 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Lansing 1989, 1993, 2 items (Box 1)
    - Milan Prison Branch 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Break-ins 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Building Documents 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Calendars 1992-1996 (Box 1)
  - Charter November 1918 (Box 1)
    (Bd oversized)
  - Committees
    - Building 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Executive, Oath of Office 1993 (Box 1)
    - Freedom Fund 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - General Lists 1988-1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Health 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Community 1994-1998 (Box 1)
  - Constitution and By-laws 1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming and Outgoing 1988-1997, 7 folders (Box 1)
    - Incoming / Agenda Items 1991-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Elections 1986-1996 (Box 1)
  - Fair Housing Center 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Financial 1987-1996 (Box 1)
  - History and Organizational Resume undated (Box 1)
  - Interns (Box 1)
  - Lists, Membership 1983-1994 (Box 1)
  - Lists, Miscellaneous (includes black churches, Michigan branches) (Box 1)
  - Membership Reports 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Midwest Public Interest Law Conference 1993 (Box 1)
  - Million Man March Association
    - By-laws 1996 (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Million Women March, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Minutes (General Membership and Executive)
    - January-February 1981 (Box 2)
    - 1987-1996, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - National
    - Annual Conference 1987-1995, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports 1987-1992 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Guidelines 1985-1993 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters 1987-1993, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1983-1996, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Obituaries, Services, Deceased Members 1992-1997 (Box 2)
  - Press Releases and Flyers 1988-1995 (Box 2)
  - Retreat 1994 (Box 2)
  - Scholarships (Box 2)
  - State (Box 3)
    - Annual Conference 1985, 1993 (Box 3)
    - Newsletters 1977-1995 (scattered) (Box 3)
    - Resolutions 1984-1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Thalheimer Award Applications 1990, 1992, 1994, 1995, 1998 (Box 3)
- Activities
  The Activities series offers further insight into initiatives associated both with the national mission and the local mission. Printed programs for the Freedom Day Dinner, for example, include summaries of branch accomplishments, provide evidence of community participation, and include tributes paid to civil rights advocates. There are also files for media, education and other forums, black history week celebrations, parent involvement days, legislative projects. Youth activities are particularly well documented in youth council files and files for ACT-SO (Afro-American Academic, Cultural, Technological and Scientific Olympics). Attention paid to political matters is also well represented in papers regarding candidate's forums and legislative mobilizations.
  - Act-So (Afro-Academic Cultural, Technological and Scientific Olympics) 1990-1998 (Box 3)
  - Bank Fair 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Bankers Forum 1993 (Box 3)
  - Black Dollar Week 1989-1993 (Box 3)
  - Black History Month 1989, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Black Jewish Coalition 1990-1994 (Box 3)
  - Cabaret 1995 (Box 3)
  - Candidate's Forum 1992-1993, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Community, General 1991-1996 (Box 3)
  - Community Health Coalition (Box 3)
  - Community Reinvestment (Box 3)
  - Drill Team 1996 (Box 3)
  - Educational Forum 1993 (Box 3)
  - Essay Contest 1993 (Box 3)
  - Flyers, Publicity (Box 3)
  - Freedom Day Dinner
    - 1987-1995 (Box 3)
    - Programs 1987-1994, 1996, 1998, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Heritage Festival 1996 (Box 3)
  - Jackson, Jesse Visit 1998 (Box 3)
  - Jubilee Day 1989-1994 (Box 3)
  - Legislative Mobilization 1989 (Box 3)
  - March on Washington (30th Anniversary March) 1993 (Box 3)
  - Media Forum 1993 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - National African American Parent Involvement Day 1994-1998 (Box 4)
  - Open House 1996 (Box 4)
  - Pastoral Brunch 1995 (Box 4)
  - PEACE (People, Equity, Activism, Commitment, Education) 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Political 1996 (Box 4)
  - Political, Phone Results 1994 (Box 4)
  - Scholarship Forum 1993 (Box 4)
  - Smiles Across the Miles 1988 (Box 4)
  - South Side Project 1988 (Box 4)
  - Women's Forum 1993 (Box 4)
  - Youth Council 1988-1992 (Box 4)
- Issues
  The Issues series, although slight in size, is important for understanding the responsive and activist role assumed by the organization on behalf of individual citizen's civil rights. Responding sometimes to news reports, sometimes to phone calls of complaints placed to the office, and sometimes to legislative movements, the branch addressed discrimination occurring in wide-ranging arenas. For some, like the Ann Arbor rapist investigation in 1995 and 1996, there are several folders of press releases, correspondence, police reports, and clippings. For others a single folder or page documents discrimination in a work setting or place of commerce.
  - Ann Arbor Rapist 1995-1996
    - Clippings (Box 4)
    - Coalition for Community Unity (Box 4)
    - Legal, Police, Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Press Releases (Box 4)
  - Bookmobile 1994 (Box 4)
  - Chavis, Benjamin 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Clippings 1990-1994 (Box 4)
  - Complaint Reports 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Cross Burning, Augusta Township 1995 (Box 4)
  - Davis, Ossie 1993 (Box 4)
  - Drive By Shooting 1995 (Box 4)
  - Eastern Michigan: Native American Nicknames and Symbols 1991 (Box 4)
  - Education and Affirmative Action 1983 (Box 4)
  - Firefighters, Ypsilanti 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Full Circle Community Center 1994 (Box 4)
  - General Motors Willow Run Plant 1992 (Box 4)
  - Green, Malice Case 1996 (Box 4)
  - Harriet Liquor Store 1994 (Box 4)
  - Matlock, John 1996 (Box 4)
  - Mayor Homel Remarks 1995 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Murders 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Non-Discriminatory Ordinance 1997 (Box 4)
  - Recall, School Board 1993 (Box 4)
  - Violence 1994 (Box 4)
  - Youth Rape Trial 1996 (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series is mainly comprised of three folders of unidentified color snapshots. Most document group activities, such as the Million Man March in Washington D. C., 1996. There is also a file of prints taken at the NAACP branch at Milan, Michigan Prison and one holding miscellaneous photographs, some of which are reproduced in the Thalheimer Award applications. The later include images of ACT-SO and youth activities, formal dinners, and informal gatherings.
  - Milan, Michigan Prison Branch undated (Box 4)
  - Million Man circa March, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous circa 1991-1992, undated (Box 4)